<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Plain account of the persecution now laid to the charge of the Church of England</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28137</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8202801</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204240</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248508346</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2339</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08202801</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28137)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1237:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Plain account of the persecution now laid to the charge of the Church of England</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  History.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204240:1"/>
            <head>A Plain Account of the <hi>Persecution,</hi> now laid to the Charge of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. THE desire of <hi>Liberty</hi> to serve God in that way and manner, which Men judge to be most acceptable to him, is so Natural and Reasonable, that they cannot but be extremely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked against those who would force them to serve him in any other. But the conceit withall, which most men have that their way of serving God is the only acceptable way; naturally inclines them, when they have Power, to use all means to constrain all others to serve him in that way only. So that <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> is not more desired by all, at one time, than it is denied by the very same Persons at another. Put them into different Conditions, and they are not of the same mind: but have different inclinations, in one state, from what they have in another. As will be apparent by a short view of what hath passed in these Churches and Kingdoms, within our memory.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Before the late Civil Wars there were very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Complaints made of the <hi>Bishops;</hi> that they pressed the Ceremonies so strictly, as to inflict heavy Censures upon those called <hi>Puritans,</hi> who could not in <hi>conscience</hi> conform to them. Now no sooner had those very Persons who thus complain'd, got their liberty to do as they pleased, but they took it quite away from the other: and Sequestred all those who would not enter into their <hi>Holy League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> for the Reforming all things, according to the Modell which they propounded. Nay, they were not willing to bear with <hi>Five</hi> Dissenting Brethren among themselves; who could not Conform to the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> Government. And when these Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting Brethren, commonly known by the Name of <hi>Independents,</hi> had got a Party strong enough, which carried all before them; they would not allow the use of the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in any Parish; no not to the <hi>King</hi> himself in his own Chapel: not grant to one of the old Clergy, so much liberty as to teach a School, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which things I do not mention (God knows) to reproach those who were guilty of them; but only to put them in mind of their own Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: that they may be humbled for them, and not insult over the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor severely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid them with that, which when time was, they acted with a higher hand themselves. If I should report all that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> did here and in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and all that the <hi>Independents</hi> did here and in <hi>New-England;</hi> it would not be thought that I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Truth, when I say they have been more guilty of this fault, than those whom they now charge with it. Which doth not excuse the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it must be confessed; but doth in some measure, mitigate her fault. For the Conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Clergy having met with such very hard usage in that dismal time, wherein many of them were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed above measure: no wonder if the smart of it, then fresh in their minds, something imbittered their spirits; when God was pleased, by a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Revolution, to put them into Power again.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Then a stricter <hi>Act of Ʋniformity</hi> was made, and several Laws pursuant to it, for the enforcing that Uniformity, by severe Penalties. But let it be remembred that none were by those Laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to come Church; but had <hi>Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ty</hi> left them to serve God at home (and some Company with them) in their own way. And let it be farther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that the reason why they were denied their liberty of meeting in greater Assemblies was; because such Assemblies were represented as <hi>greatly endangering the publick Peace and Safety:</hi> as the words are in the very first Act of this nature against <hi>Quakers,</hi> in the Year 1662. Let any one read the <hi>Oxford Act,</hi> (as it is commonly called) made in the Year 1665. and that at <hi>Westminster</hi> in the Year 1670. and he will find them intended against <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Conventicles;</hi> That is, they who made them were perswaded by the <hi>Jesuit interest</hi> at first to look upon such Meetings as <hi>Nurseries of Sedition,</hi> where bad <hi>Principles</hi> were infused into mens minds, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to the <hi>Civil Government.</hi> If it had not been f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r this, it doth not appear that the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of these <hi>Laws</hi> were inclined to such <hi>Severities</hi> as were thereby enacted; but the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> might have enjoyed a larger liberty in <hi>Religion.</hi> It was not <hi>Religion</hi> alone which was considered, and pretended, but the <hi>publick peace and settlement:</hi> with respect to which they were tyed up so straitly in the exercise of their <hi>Religion.</hi> Which, to deal clearly, I do not believe would have taught <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> but this was constantly insinuated by the <hi>Court A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents;</hi> and it is no <hi>wonder</hi> if the <hi>Parliament</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred how the Ministers of that Persuasion (Though indeed from the then appearance of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi>) had been the principal Incouragers of that <hi>Defensive War</hi> against the <hi>King,</hi> were easily made to believe that they still retained the same <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and would propagate them, if they were suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, among the People. Certain it is also, that the <hi>Court</hi> made it their care to have those Acts pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; though at the same time they hindred their execution: that they might keep up both Parties, in the height of their Animosities; and especially that they might make the Church of <hi>England,</hi> be both, hated and despised by the <hi>Dissenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. Thus things continued for some time, till wise men began to see into the Secret; and think of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204240:2"/> a <hi>Reconciliation.</hi> But it was always hindred by the <hi>Court:</hi> who never thought of giving <hi>Liberty</hi> by a <hi>Law,</hi> but only by the <hi>Prerogative;</hi> which could as easily take it away. There was a time, for instance, when a <hi>Comprehension,</hi> &amp;c. was projected by several Great Men both in <hi>Church and State:</hi> for the taking as many as was possible into Union with us; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding Ease for the rest. Which so netled the late <hi>King,</hi> that meeting with the then Archbishop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> he said to him (as I perfectly remember) <hi>What, My Lord, you are for a Comprehension?</hi> To which he making such a reply as signified, he heard some were about it: <hi>No,</hi> said the King, <hi>I will keep the Church of</hi> England <hi>pure and unmixed:</hi> that is, never suffer a Reconciliation with the <hi>Dissenters.</hi> And when the <hi>Lords and Cimmons</hi> also had, not many years ago, passed a Bill for the repealing of the most heavy of all the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> against <hi>Dissenters,</hi> viz. the Statute of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. (which, by the Parliament is made, against the <hi>Wicked and dangerous practices of Sedicious Sectaries, and disloyal persons</hi>) his late Majesty so dealt with the Clerk of the Parliament, that it was shuffled <hi>away</hi> and could not be found; when it was to have been p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>esented to him, among other Bills, for his Royal Consent unto it. A notable to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the abhorrence the Court then had of all <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws;</hi> and of their great kindness to <hi>Dissenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. Who may remember, if they please, that as once there was a time, when the Court turned our, or chid, those <hi>Justices,</hi> who were forward in the Execution of the Laws against <hi>Nonconformists;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they were then in so low a Condition, that the Court was afraid the Church of <hi>England</hi> might indeed be established in its Uniformity. So when the <hi>Nonconformists</hi> were, by some liberty, grown stronger, and set themselves against the Court In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, in the Election of <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> and such like things; then all those <hi>Justices</hi> were turned out who hung back, and would not execute the <hi>Laws</hi> against them; and <hi>Justices</hi> pickt out for the purpose, who would do it severely. Nay, the Clergy were called upon, and had Orders sent them, to return the Names of all <hi>Nonconformists</hi> in their several Parishes; that they might be proceeded against in the <hi>Courts Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</hi> And here I cannot forget the Order made by the <hi>Middlesex Justices,</hi> at the Sessions at <hi>Hickes-Hall, Jan.</hi> 13 1681. where they urge the Execution of the Act of 22 <hi>C.</hi> 2. against <hi>Conventicles,</hi> because <hi>in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability they will destroy both Church and State.</hi> This was the reason which moved them to call upon <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables</hi> and all other <hi>Officers</hi> to do their duty in this matter: Nay, to call upon the <hi>B. of London</hi> himself, that <hi>he would use his utmost endeavours, within his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction, that all such persons may be Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi> This was a bold stroke, proceeding from an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usual degree of Zeal: which plainly enough signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies that the <hi>Bishops</hi> were not so forward as the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices,</hi> in the prosecuting of <hi>Dissenters.</hi> Who may do well to remember that the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> a little before this, had been so Kind to them, that those <hi>Justices</hi> would not have dared to have been so severe as they were at <hi>Hickes-Hall,</hi> if they had not been set on by directions from <hi>Whitehall.</hi> For in their <hi>Order</hi> they press the Execution of the Statute <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. for levying <hi>Twelve-pence</hi> a <hi>Sunday</hi> upon all those that do not come to Church: Whereas the <hi>House of Commons, Nov.</hi> 6. 1680. had, <hi>Resolved,</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine contra dicente, <hi>that it is the Opinion of this House, That the Acts of Parliament made in the Reign of Q.</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>and King</hi> James, <hi>against Popish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusants, ought not to be extended against Protestant Dissenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. Who should not forget how backward the Clergy of <hi>London</hi> especially, were to comply with this design, of reviving the Execution of the <hi>Laws</hi> against them; <hi>what courses they took to save them from this danger! and what hatred they incurred for being so kind to them! Which in truth was kindness to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; for new they saw plainly enough that Nothing was intended but the destruction of us both, by setting us, in our turns, one against the other. Many indeed were possessed with the old Opinion, that the Dissenters aimed at the overthrow of the Government both in Church and State: which made them the more readily joyn with those who were employed to suppress them, by turning the edge of the Laws upon them. But both these were most industriously promoted by the Court: Who laboured might and main to have this believed, that they who were called</hi> Whigs, <hi>intended the ruine of the Church and of the Monarchy too: and therefore none had the Court favour, but they alone who were for the ruining of</hi> them. <hi>All others were frown'd upon, and branded with the name of</hi> Trimmers; <hi>who they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured at last, to say were worse than</hi> Whigs. <hi>Mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly because they, seeing through the design, desired those ugly Names of</hi> Whig <hi>and</hi> Tory <hi>might be laid aside; and perswaded all to</hi> Moderation, Love, Unity, <hi>and</hi> Peace. <hi>If any man had these dangerous words in his mouth, he had a mark set upon him; and was lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as an enemy, as soon as he discovered any desires of Reconciliation.</hi> No peace with Dissenters <hi>was then as much in some mens mouths, as</hi> no peace with Rome <hi>had been in others. They were all voted to destruction; and it was an unpardonable crime so much as to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion an Accommodation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such things as these ought not to be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. But if they list not to call them to mind, (tho' they be of fresh memory) yet let the at least consider what they have had at their Tongues end, ever since they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204240:2"/> knew any thing: That <hi>the Church of Rome is a persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Church, and the Mother of Persecution.</hi> Will they then be deluded by the present <hi>Sham</hi> of <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science;</hi> which they of that Church pretend to give? It is not in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>power,</hi> no more than in their <hi>Spirit:</hi> They neither <hi>will</hi> nor <hi>can</hi> give liberty of Conscience; but with a design to take all liberty from us. That Church must be obeye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and there is no middle choice among them, between <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n or burn, conform or be undone.</hi> What Liberty <hi>do</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> give in any Country, where thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>power</hi> is established? What Liberty <hi>can</hi> they give, who have determined that Hereticks ought to be rooted out? Look into <hi>France</hi> (with which we have had the strict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Alliance &amp; Friendship a long time) and behold, how at this moment they compel those to go to <hi>Mass;</hi> who they know abhor it as an abominable Idolatry. Such a violent <hi>Spirit</hi> now acts them, that they stick not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane their own most <hi>holy Mysteries;</hi> that they may have the face of an <hi>Ʋniversal Conformity,</hi> without the least <hi>Liberty.</hi> For the <hi>new Converts,</hi> as they are called, poor Wretches, are known to be mere <hi>outward Compliers:</hi> in their Hearts abominating that which they are forced externally to Worship. They declare as much by es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caping from this Tyranny over their Consciences, and bewailing their sinful compliance; whensoever they have an opportunity. And they that cannot escape, frequently protest they have been constrained to adore that, which they believe ought not to be adored. And when they come to dye, refuse to receive the <hi>Romish Sacrament;</hi> and thereupon are dragg'd, when dead, along the Streets, and thrown, like dead Dogs upon the Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hills. Unto what a heigth of rage are the spirits of the <hi>Romish Clergy</hi> inflamed; that it perfectly blinds their eyes; and will not let them see how they expose the most sacred thing in all their <hi>Religion</hi> (the <hi>Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which they believe to be <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> himself) to be received by those who they know have no reverence at all for it, but utterly abhor it? For they force them, by all manner of violence, to adore the <hi>Host</hi> against their will, and then to eat what they have adored; tho' they have the greatest reason to believe, that those poor Creatures do not adore it. That is, the Chuch of <hi>Rome</hi> will have her Mysteries adored by all, tho' it be by <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites.</hi> None shall be excused, but whether they <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> or not believe, they shall be compelled to <hi>do</hi> as that Church doth. Nothing shall hinder it; for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and fury wherewith they are now transported, is so exceeding great; that it makes them (as I have said) offer <hi>violence</hi> even to their own Religion, rather than suffer any body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot to conform to it.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. And assure your selves they are very desirous to extend this Violence beyond the bounds of <hi>France.</hi> They would fain see <hi>England</hi> also, in the same condition. The Bishop of <hi>Valence</hi> and <hi>Die,</hi> hath told us as much, in the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>peech which he made to the <hi>French King,</hi> in the Name of the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> to Congratulate his glorious Atchievements, in rooting out the Heresie of <hi>Calvin.</hi> In which he hath a most memorable Passage, for which we are beholden to him because it informs us that they are not satisfied with what their King hath done there; but would have him think there is a further Glory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served for him, of lending his help to make us such good Catholicks, as he hath made in <hi>France.</hi> This is the blessed Work they would be at: and if any among us be still so blind as not to see it, we must look upon it as the just judgment of God upon them for some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sins which they have committed. They are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up to a Reprobate mind, which cannot discern the most evident things. They declare to all the World that they have been above <hi>fifty</hi> years, crying out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst they know not what. For they know not what <hi>Popery</hi> is (of which they have seemed to be horribly afraid) if they believe that they of that Religion either can or will give any <hi>Liberty;</hi> when they have <hi>power</hi> to Establish their <hi>Tyranny.</hi> It is no better: St. <hi>John</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self hath described that Church under the Name of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> that cruel City; and of a BEAST, which like a <hi>Bear,</hi> tramples all under its feet; and of <hi>another Beast, which causes as many as will not worship the Image of the Beast, to be killed; and that no man may buy or sell save such as have had his mark; i. e.</hi> are of his Rellgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1.15, 16. This Character they will make good to the very end of their Reign, as they have ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled it from the beginning. They cannot alter their nature, no more than the <hi>Ethiopian change his Skin, or the Leopard his Spots.</hi> It ever was, since the rise of the BEAST, &amp; it ever will be till its fall, a bloody Church. Which can bear no contradiction to her Doctrine and Orders, but will endeavour to root out all those that oppose her, from the face of the Earth. Witness the Barbarous <hi>Crusado's</hi> against the poor <hi>Albigenses</hi> in <hi>France:</hi> in one of which alone <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himself saith, and not without Triumph, there were killed no less than an <hi>hundred thousand.</hi> Witness the horrible <hi>but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries</hi> committed in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> &amp; in the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> in the Age before us; and in <hi>Poland,</hi> the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> &amp; in <hi>Ireland</hi> in this Age; upon those who had no other fault but this, that they made the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and not the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> the Rule of their faith.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>IX. But if you be Ignorant of what hath been done, &amp; is doing abroad, yet I hope you observe what they do here at home. What do you think of the</hi> Declaration <hi>which was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lately imposed to be read in all our Churches? Which when several</hi> Bishops <hi>and their Clergy, most humbly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented, they could not</hi> in Conscience <hi>publish to the people in time of Divine Service; this would not excuse them; their Petition was received with indignation, and lookt upon as a Libel; the</hi> Bishops <hi>were prosecuted for it; and Inquiry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204240:3"/> is now ordered to be made after those who did not read it (as well as those that did) that they may be punished by the</hi> High Commissioners. <hi>Call you this Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science? Or do you imagine you shall never have any thing imposed upon you, to be read in your Congregations, which you cannot comply withall? Consider, I beseech you, what will become of you when that time shall come? What's the meaning of this, that ever they are lookt upon as Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, for following their</hi> Conscience, <hi>whose services have been acknowledged to be so great, that they should never be forgotten? It ought to teach</hi> Dissenters <hi>what they are to expect hereafter, when they have served them so far, (by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the</hi> Tests <hi>and the</hi> Penal Laws) <hi>as to enable them with safety to remember all their former pretended trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions. Let them assure themselves the</hi> services <hi>of the Church of</hi> England <hi>are not now more certainly forgotten, than the</hi> Sins <hi>of</hi> Dissenters <hi>will hereafter, when they have got power to punish them, be most certainly remembred. Be not drawn in then by</hi> deceitful words, <hi>to help forward your own destruction. If you will not be assistant to it, they cannot do it alone: and it will be very strange if you be perswaded to lend them your help, when the deceit is so ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent. For what are all the present pleas for</hi> Liberty, <hi>but so many infamous</hi> Libels <hi>upon the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, which denies all men this Liberty? While they declaim so laudly against</hi> Persecution, <hi>they most notoriously reproach</hi> Popery; <hi>which subsists by Nothing but</hi> deceit <hi>and</hi> cruelty. <hi>And who can think that they would suffer their Church to be so exposed and reviled, as it is by such discourses, but with a design to cheat heedless people into its obedience? For this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd they can hear it proved, nay prove it themselves to be an</hi> Antichristian Church; <hi>when they prove it is against</hi> Christianity, <hi>nay against the Law of</hi> Nature <hi>and</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reason, <hi>to trouble any body for his opinion in Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>X. Once more then I beseech you, be not deceived by good words, if you l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve your</hi> Liberty, <hi>and your</hi> Life. <hi>Call to mind how our poor Brethren in</hi> France <hi>were very lately deluded by the repeated Protestations which their King made, he would observe the Edict of</hi> Nantes <hi>(which was the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Liberty) even then, when he was about to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow it: &amp; by many assurances, which were given them by those who came to torment them, that the King</hi> intended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o reform the Church of <hi>France,</hi> as soon as he had u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited his Subjects. <hi>What he had done already against the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>they told them was an instance of it; and they should shortly see other matters. Such en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>snaring words they heard</hi> there <hi>daily from the mouths of their armed Persecutors, who were ready to fall upon them, or had begun to oppress them: And therefore they would be arrant fools</hi> here, <hi>if they did not give good words, when they have no power to hurt us. But we shall be far greater fools if we believe they will keep their word when they have got th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t power; the greatest of all fools if we give them that power. They have no other way but this, to wheedle us out of our</hi> Laws <hi>and</hi> Liberties. <hi>Do but surrender the one, I mean our</hi> Laws; <hi>and they will soon take awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the other, our beloved</hi> Liberties. <hi>Be not tempted to make such a dangerous Experiment: but let the</hi> Laws <hi>stand as they are, because they</hi> are <hi>against</hi> them <hi>(as appears by their earnest endeavours to repeal them) and be not used as tools to take them away, because they</hi> have <hi>been grievous to</hi> you. <hi>They never can be so again. For can they who now Court you have the face to turn them again upon you, after they have made all this noise for Liberty? And the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>you may be assured, will not any more trouble you: but when a Protestant Prince shall come, will joyn in the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all our breaches; by removing all things out of the way, which have long hindred that blessed work. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not meet together in a body to give you this assurance (how should they without the Kings authority so to do?) but every particular person that I have discoursed withall, which are not a few (&amp; you your selves would do well to ask them, when you meet them) profess that they see an absolute necessity of making an end of these Differences that have almost un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done us: and will no longer contend to bring all men to</hi> one Uniformity; <hi>but promote an</hi> Uniform Liberty. <hi>Do not imagine I intend to give mere words: I mean honest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; such a regular</hi> Liberty, <hi>as will be the beauty and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, not the blot and discredit of our Religion. To such a</hi> temper <hi>the Archbishop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>with several other Bishops of his Province, and their</hi> Clergy, <hi>have openly declared they are willing to come. And the Bishops and Clergy of the Church of</hi> England <hi>have never been known to act deceitfully. Our Religion will not at any time allow them to</hi> equivocate; <hi>nor to give good words without a meaning. Much less at such a time as this when our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in great danger; and we have nothing to trust unto, but Gods protection of sincere Persons.</hi> Let Integ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity and Uprightness preserve us, <hi>is their constant Prayer. They can hope for no help from Heaven, if they should prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with men. God they know would desert them, if they should go about to delude their Brethren. And they are not so void of common sense, as to adventure to incur his most high displeasure, when they have nothing to rely upon but his favour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In short,</hi> Trust <hi>to those who own you for their</hi> Brethren, <hi>as you do them: for thô they have been</hi> angry <hi>Brethren, ye<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> there is hope of Reconciliation between such near Relations But put no Confidence in those, who not only utterly disown any such Relation to you, but have ever treated you with an implacable hatred, as their most mortal</hi> Enemies; <hi>unto whom it is impossible they should be reconciled.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Prov. 12.19, 20. </bibl>
                  <hi>The lips of Truth shall be established for ever: but a lying Tongue is but for a moment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lying lips are an abomination to the Lord: but the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> that deal Truly are his delight.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>